Appleton Company Records 6516
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Appleton Company Records
1815-1925
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Appleton Company
6516
3 cubic feet
2.7 linear ft.
Account books, correspondence, daybooks, records (documents), minutes.
Records, correspondence and daybooks of the Appleton mills in Lowell, MA.
10065772
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 11, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 13, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Incorporated in 1828 by members of the Proprietors of Locks and Canals, among whom William and Nathan Appleton, John Lowell, Jr., William Sturgis and Thomas Perkins served as officers, the Appleton Company occupied two mills on the Hamilton Canal in Lowell. In 1832, the mill employed 480 operatives and had 400 looms and 11,776 spindles producing 520,000 yards of sheeting, shirtings and drillings annually. By 1874 there were 764 looms and 27,568 spindles. Operations ceased at the Lowell site in the early 1920s. J. P. Stevens Company purchased the surviving South Carolina division in 1925.
Scope and Contents
Contains one production volume of an inventory of stock and finished goods, two daybooks, and a one volume copybook addition to Superintendent George Motley's correspondence, minutes of meetings of stockholders, and petitions submitted. Also contains deeds; patent assignments; insurance agreements; mill construction records; property, machinery, and power plant files; information files concerning New England mills; papers concerning the Proprietors of Locks & Canals; incoming correspondence to treasurer; incoming correspondence to Nathan Appleton. Also lists of goods purchased, contracts, employee information files, wages and payrolls, overseers' records, statements of cloth manufactured, spinning records, and weaving records.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I. ORGANIZATION AND ADMINISTRATION
Sub-Series A. BOARD OF DIRECTORS AND STOCKHOLDERS RECORDS Sub-Series B. LEGAL AND PROPERTY
Series II. EXECUTIVE
Series III. FINANCIAL
Series IV. PURCHASING
Series V. SALES
Series VI. LABOR
Series VII. PRODUCTION
Boardinghouses; Business records; Cotton manufacture; Cotton technology, General; Drills (cloth); Hours of labor; Industries; Labor records; Manufacturers' agents; Mill agents; Mill superintendents; Minutes.; Overseers; Payrolls; Personnel records; Petitions; Sheeting (Textile fabric); Shirting (Textile fabric); Strikes and lockouts; Ten hour movement; Textile industry; Textile workers; Wages; Appleton, Nathan, 1779-1861; Appleton, William, 1747-1785; Lowell, John, Jr.; Motley, George.; Perkins, Thomas.; Sturgis, William, 1782-1863; J.P. Stevens & Co.; Proprietors of the Locks and Canals on Merrimack River; Suffolk Manufacturing Company (Lowell, Mass.)
10065772
- Series I. ORGANIZATION AND ADMINISTRATION
  - Sub-Series A. BOARD OF DIRECTORS AND STOCKHOLDERS RECORDS
    - Minutes of Stockholders Meetings, 1827-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Early proprietors records and act of incorporation; list of company officers from 1828-1888
    - Revision of Bylaws, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Committee Report on Waterpower, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      By Mr. Cary. October 1842.
    - Statement of Valuation Committee on Cost and Value of Appleton Company, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      December 31, 1832.
    - Report of the Committee on Waterpower, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      December 12, 1843.
    - Report on New Mill Costs and Value, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      June 16, 1846.
    - Report of the Committee on Valuation of Property, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      April 1, 1857.
    - Report of the Appleton Company to Patent Office, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      September 20, 1857.
    - Report of the Committee on Transfer of Accounts, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      April 1, 1861.
    - Committee Report on System of Treasurer as Selling Agent, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      June 25, 1867.
    - Petition by Suffolk Weavers Against Wage Reduction, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      February 1834. Requests Appleton weavers to join their strike.
    - Petition by Boarding House Matrons to Increase Boarding Charge, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      July 8, 1835.
    - Petition by Boarding House Matrons to Increase Boarding Charge (Box 1, Folder 12)
      After 1835.
    - Operatives' Petition for Reduction from 11 to 10 Hours, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      February 11, 1867.
    - Stock Subscription Announcement, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      May 30, 1827. Circular by Proprietors of Locks and Canals.
    - Stock Subscription Lists, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      January 2, 1839; January 12, 1839; January 28, 1839
    - Correspondence Regarding Stock Transfers, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      June 15, 1854.
    - Bond Securing Appleton From Loss in Stock Transfers, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      March 24, 1986.
    - Correspondence Regarding Liability of Directors to Stockholders, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      February 25, 1904.
  - Sub-Series B. LEGAL AND PROPERTY
    - Original Deed of Mill Privilege and Second Deed of Mill Privilege, 1826-1833 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      April 29, 1826 and August 10, 1833.
    - Deed From Proprietors of Mill Pond Wharf Company, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      November 10, 1836
    - Proposal For Sale of Mill Power or Mill Privilege, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      June 24, 1843.
    - Proposal For Sale of Mill Power, Mill Privilege, and Land, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      November 29, 1843.
    - Bill of Sale for Land Sold by the Appleton Company, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      June 1, 1845.
    - Copy of Release of Proprietors of Locks and Canals From Original Agreement for Sale of Mill Power and New Indenture For Sale of Mill Power, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Report on New Indenture to the Proprietors of the Locks and Canals, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      June 13, 1854.
    - Deed: Samuel T. Snow House to the Appleton Company, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      January 19, 1856.
    - Correspondence Regarding the Purchase of a House by Superintendent George Motley, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      June 11, 1859.
    - Agent's House Sold to Superintendent George Motley, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      November 3, 1862.
    - Regulations on the Use of Surplus Water Power, 1870-1886 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      November 3, 1870: Surplus water power at Lowell; January 7, 1875: Regulations under which surplus water power is permitted to be used; February 17, 1885: Report of Committee on Surplus Power; February 17, 1885: Charges for the surplus power used in 1881
    - Petition to the City of Lowell for Damages Caused by the Diversion of Water, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      April 1, 1873.
    - Indenture to the City of Lowell Regarding Land Taken by the City, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      December 31, 1875.
    - Release of Water Rights to the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      April 17, 1896.
    - Quitclaim Deed, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      July 3, 1920.
    - Lease of Brown's Wharf, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      February 15, 1828.
    - Lease of Brown's Wharf, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      April 1, 1835.
    - Agreement Regarding Blackman's Patent Loom Improvement, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      May 17, 1836.
    - Patent Assignment: William G. Leonard's Railway Drawing Head, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      September 28, 1848
    - License: Uriah A. Boyden's Axle Bearings, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      March 13, 1849.
    - Patent Assignment: Oliver Pearl's Bobbins, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      May 23, 1851.
    - License: Babbitt's Patent Boxes for Axles, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      September 1, 1854.
    - License: Whiting Hayden Regulators, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      June 24, 1852.
    - Patent Assignment: Zebulon Lyford's Loom Pickers, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      May 29, 1858.
    - License: Silas Durgin's Measuring Machine, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      October 4, 1858.
    - Patent Transfers: Card Strippers, 1860-1875 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      April 20, 1860; August 21, 1860; December 2, 1861; February 10 1862; April 16, 1874; October 27, 1874; February 8, 1875; April 12, 1875.
    - License: Evan Leigh's Patent for Top Rollers, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      May 14, 1861.
    - Patent Transfer: Daniel Hussey's Double Cone Bobbins, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      September 26, 1863.
    - License: E. D. and George Draper's Top Rolls, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      December 28, 1865.
    - License: E. D. and George Draper's Stop Motion, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - License: William C. Davol's Positive Cam Shaft Motion, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      September 26, 1866.
    - License: E. D. and George Draper's Drawing Regulators, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      December 6, 1866.
    - License: George Draper and Son's Loom Improvements, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      May 25, 1868.
    - License: Myron Haskell's Shuttle Binders, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      May 13, 1870.
    - License: Richard Collins' Harness Motion, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 44)
      June 23, 1870.
    - License: Edmund Graham and Wanton Rouse's Picker Staff Motions, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      June 15, 1872 and June 24, 1873.
    - Patent Transfer: John M. Pevey's Mangle Racks and Pinion, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      June 14,1882.
    - Patent Transfer: Jesse Cottrell's Loom Attachment, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      June 1, 1885.
    - Final Settlement of Oliver Pearl Patent Case, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      July 21, 1881. Oliver Pearl Spinning Patents.
    - Liability Release Form, 1870-1880 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Circa 1870s.
    - Lowell Abatements, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      September 10, 1910.
    - Transcript: Hamilton Manufacturing and Appleton Manufacturing vs. City of Lowell, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      December 16, 1902. Case nos. 1617 and 1620. Index to page 200.
    - Transcript: Hamilton Manufacturing and Appleton Manufacturing vs. City of Lowell, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      December 16, 1902. Case nos. 1617 and 1620. Pages 201 to page 399.
    - Transcript: Hamilton Manufacturing and Appleton Manufacturing vs. City of Lowell, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      December 16, 1902. Case nos. 1617 and 1620. Pages 400 to page 599.
    - Transcript: Hamilton Manufacturing and Appleton Manufacturing vs. City of Lowell, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      December 16, 1902. Case nos. 1617 and 1620. Pages 600 to page 799.
    - Transcript: Hamilton Manufacturing and Appleton Manufacturing vs. City of Lowell, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      December 16, 1902. Case nos. 1617 and 1620. Pages 800 to page 999.
    - Transcript: Hamilton Manufacturing and Appleton Manufacturing vs. City of Lowell, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      December 16, 1902. Case nos. 1617 and 1620. Pages 1000 to page 1180 (end).
- Series II. EXECUTIVE
  - Cost of Manufacturing, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    For six months ending May 1842.
  - Cost of Cloth, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    For six months ending May 27, 1843.
  - Manufacturing Costs, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    March 1843. Broken down y Department.
  - Cost of Waste Cloth per Yard, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Cost of Cloth, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    For six months ending March 25, 1867.
  - Cost of Manufacturing, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    January through April 1868.
  - Cost of Cloth, 1867-1870 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Cost of Cloth, 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    June 14, 1850.
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    August 11, 1855.
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    September 15, 1859.
  - Memo of Agreement Regarding Use of Wool by Companies, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    November 2, 1864.
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    December 7, 1864.
  - Notification of Withdrawal of Tremont Mills From Mutual Insurance, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    August 8, 1871.
  - Notification of Withdrawal of Suffolk Mills From Mutual Insurance, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Request of Suffolk and Tremont Mills to Re-enter Mutual Insurance, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    September 22, 1871.
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    November 6, 1873.
  - Recommendation of the Committee on the Introduction of Additional Sprinklers, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    July 26, 1877.
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    October 1, 1877.
  - Mutual Insurance Agreement, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    December 6, 1884.
  - Memo of Machinery to be Furnished Each Mill by Proprietors of Locks and Canals, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Memo of Articles Purchased by Proprietors of Locks and Canals, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    October 9, 1828. To be used in Appleton.
  - Contract to Dig Well, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    October 21, 1828.
  - Number of Bricks Used in Cotton Storehouse, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    December 27, 1828. Account of bricks received and used.
  - Construction Bill from Proprietors of Locks and Canals, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    May 30, 1829.
  - Memo of Cost of Mills Gearing and Housing by Mr. Boott, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    June 1829.
  - Bill for Mill Powers, Mill Construction, and Machinery from Proprietors of Locks and Canals, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    November 1829.
  - Memo of Window Caps and Sills, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    December 17, 1829.
  - Copy of Bill for Covering Rollers at Merrimack Manufacturing Company Mill no.2, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    January 10, 1830.
  - Copy of Bill for Covering Rollers at Hamilton Manufacturing Company Mill no.3, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    July 26, 1830.
  - Sketch of Steam Boiler in Sizing Room, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    December 2, 1830.
  - Depth and Location of Wells (Box 1, Folder 87)
    No Date.
  - Lumber Weights (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Repair Bill for Fire Damage, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    July 22, 1837.
  - Correspondence Regarding Water Pipes, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 90)
    July 19, 1839.
  - Construction Labor Costs, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    March 28, 1840. Especially water pipes to tenements.
  - Estimate of Brick Work on Picker House, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    April 1844.
  - Proposal for Foundation Excavation, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    July 5, 1844.
  - Cost of Picker House and Mill, 1844 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Account of Stone Work, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    October 25, 1845.
  - Estimated Cost of New Mill, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    December 16, 1845.
  - Cost of Picker House, 1844-1845 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Estimate for Taking Down and Rebuilding Mill Wall, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    November 29, 1854.
  - Cost Estimates for Addition to Mill no.1, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    April 11 and May 9, 1859. Measurements of excavation, Cement, and dry wall.
  - Estimate of Cost of Building Between Suffolk Mills (Box 1, Folder 99)
    Circa 1840-1860.
  - Estimate for Cotton House, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 100)
    March 23, 1861.
  - Agreement and Specifications to Build Cotton Store House, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    June 18, 1861
  - Labor and Construction Costs, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    December 19, 1868.
  - Building Permit, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    April 23, 1912.
  - Correspondence from Hiram F. Mills Regarding Extension of Dye House Wall, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    December 20, 1915 and January 11, 1916.
  - Estimate of Power Necessary to Run Machinery at Appleton, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Complete Inventory of Mill, Machinery, Furniture, and Stock, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    November 1832.
  - List and Valuation of Machinery, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    December 21, 1838.
  - Plan of Stoves at West End of Mill no.2, 1839 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    May 1839.
  - Draught of English Drawing, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Size and Speed of Old Drums In W. Picker no.2 Mill, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    January 1843. Before alteration.
  - List of Machinery, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    February 1844. Also number of workers in each department.
  - Prices for Machinery from Proprietors of Locks and Canals, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    March 1844.
  - Table Showing Effects of Exhaust Apparatus on Appleton Turbine, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    February 13, 1845.
  - Contract for Turbine Wheel to V. A. Boyden, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    March 27, 1845.
  - Machinery Ordered From Lowell Machine Shop, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    June 13, 1845.
  - Machinery in Mills 1 and 2, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    December 1, 1845.
  - Memo of Machinery and Power on Turbine Wheel, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Cost of Turbine Wheel for Picker House, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Machinery Ordered From Lowell Machine Shop, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    January 3, 1846.
  - Bills of Gay, Silver, and Company for Turbine Wheel, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    December 27, 1846.
  - Machinery Prices From Lowell Machine Shop, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Machinery in Mill, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Machinery in Mills no.1, 2, and 3, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    January 1, 1849.
  - Machinery in Appleton Mill, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    March 1, 1851
  - Estimate of Costs of Wheel Pits, Penstock, and Raceway at Hamilton and Appleton, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    December 7, 1953.
  - Mr. Francis' Estimate of Required Power of New Turbine, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    August 25, 1854.
  - Design of Water Wheel Shaft (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Circa 1854-1855.
  - Estimates, Specifications, Weight, and Costs of Turbine, Penstock, and Wheel Pit, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    January through September 1855.
  - Valuation of Real Estate and Machinery, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    June 1865.
  - Cost of Dynamometer, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    February 10, 1866.
  - Agreement and Memo Regarding the Purchase of Machinery form Lowell Machine Shop, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    January 1875.
  - Machinery From Lowell Machine Shop, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    July 28, 1875.
  - Plans for Water Power and Steam, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    June through October 1877.
  - Machinery Order, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Cost of Drums and Gearing (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Expenses Covering Rollers, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    February 1, 1842.
  - Cost for Covering Rollers at Merrimack (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Circulation of Waltham BMC Cloth, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    February 1828.
  - Wages Paid at Nashua, NH, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    September 15, 1828.
  - Copy of Correspondence and Circular from American Hydraulic Company, Windsor, VT, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    January 19, 1829. Regarding rotative fire engine (water pump).
  - Precautions Against Fire Adopted by Merrimack Manufacturing Company, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    January 29, 1829
  - Average of Wages at Hamilton Company, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    July 1832.
  - List of Machinery in Jackson Mills, Nashua, NH, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    December 31, 1834.
  - Statement of the Number of Help in Lawrence Mills, 1841 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    March 11, 1841.
  - Perkins, Cabot and Dwight Mills, Cabotville, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    September 1842. Wages, costs, machinery, etc.
  - Whites Mill, West Boylston, MA., 1842 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    September 1842. Machinery, cost of cloth, etc.
  - Memo About York Mills, Saco, ME, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Costs.
  - Cost of Lawrence Cloth, 1842-1843 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Draft and Twist, Manchester, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Wage Rates (Prices) at Lawrence Merrimack Mill, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    June 12, 1845.
  - Proprietors of Locks and Canals Sizing Receipt to Francis C. Lowell, 1815 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Sizing report sent to Francis Lowell 1815; cost of Waltham BMC cloth 1828; wages paid at Nashua, NH 1828; fire engine circular 1829; fire precautions at Merrimack Mfg. Co. 1832; average wages at Hamilton Mfg. Co. 1832; list of machinery in Jackson Mills,
  - Rainfall, 1831-1841 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    June 1831 through June 1841. Months of June only.
  - Mill Powers Sold by Proprietors of Locks and Canals, 1844 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Proprietors of Locks and Canals Vote Regarding Cost of Improvements, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    December 26, 1846.
  - Proprietors of Locks and Canals Vote to Limit Height for Raising Water, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    February 28, 1848.
  - Proprietors of Locks and Canals Vote to Secure Each Company Against Damages by Changes in Changes for Extension of Water Power, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    July 1, 1848.
  - Correspondence Incoming to Treasurer, 1845 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    October 7, 1845. Note concerning donation to Third Baptist Society.
  - Correspondence Incoming to Treasurer, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    October 30, 1862. Investment of the assets of the company during the Civil War.
  - Correspondence Incoming to Treasurer, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    September 18, 1914. From Proprietors of Locks and Canals regarding railroad track maintenance.
  - Correspondence Incoming to Nathan Appleton, President, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    September 2, 1853. From Treasurer regarding the 10-Hour Movement.
  - Correspondence Incoming to Nathan Appleton, President, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    January 2, 1861. Resignation of William B. Bacon as Treasurer.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1840 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    June 3, 1840. Notifying Motley of his election to Board of Trustees of the Lowell Hospital Association.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    January 9, 1846. Character reference by Motley for Appleton overseer, Richard Tripp.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    March 31, 1847. Character reference by Motley for former Appleton clerk, Mr. Metcalf.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    February 9, 1852. To J. W. Paige and Company regarding shortage in bale of cloth.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    May 16, 1857. To Hobbs regarding the "Hayden patent regulator for drawing."
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    August 6, 1859. To William B. Bacon regarding cotton shipments and prices.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    January 20, 1860. From F. F. Battles regarding amount of cotton used by Massachusetts Cotton Mills, Lowell, MA.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    November 19, 1862. From James B. Francis regarding leather belting.
  - Correspondence of J. H. Sawyer, Superintendent, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    December 14, 1867. From Edward S. Dodge regarding license prices.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    October 13, 1869. From James Manes and Son regarding waterproofing recipe.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent (Box 3, Folder 64)
    No Date. Directions for covering boilers with felt.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1831 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    December 14, 1831. From agent, P. T. Jackson, regarding bill for repairs.
  - Correspondence of George Motley, Superintendent, 1844-1869 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    Letter book
  - Agent's Correspondence, 1838 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    March 15, 1838. Regarding yarn sizing.
  - Agent's Correspondence, 1843 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    July 10, 1843. To John Clark, regarding City Hall appointments to charity board.
- Series III. FINANCIAL
  - Trial Balances, 1843-1869 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    August 30, 1843; November 25, 1865; November 30, 1969.